<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the two last things viz. resurrections and judgments at last revealed by Christ himself, as being needful points of doctrine respecting the last times of this world : set forth by question and answer ... to be added to all catechisms that have them not.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27568</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355609</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205945</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240889676</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing O144A</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">31355609</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27568)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1750:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the two last things viz. resurrections and judgments at last revealed by Christ himself, as being needful points of doctrine respecting the last times of this world : set forth by question and answer ... to be added to all catechisms that have them not.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno dom. 1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Eschatology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="question_and_answer">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205945:1"/>
            <head>Of the Two last things, <hi>viz.</hi> Resurrections and Judgments at last Revealed by Christ himself, as being needful Points of Doctrine respecting the last times of this World; set forth by <hi>Question</hi> and <hi>Answer,</hi> for the more easie Apprehension and more strong Confirmation of those great Divine Truths before Christs Revelation, darkly set down in Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as the Tract following manifiests, to be added to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Catechismes that have them not. <hi>Anno Dom. 1682.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> ARe the Resurrection of the Saints at Christs appearance in the Clouds, and the Resurrection of the Wicked at the last Trumpet, 2. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct Resurrections of the dead Bodies of Men?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> They are 2. distinct Resurrections of the dead Bodies of Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> How are they Distinguished?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. By the Persons riseing, namely of the just and unjust. 2. By the distinct ends thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> to Life, or to Condemnation. 3. By the distinct times of the first and last Resurrection, set forth by Christ himself at 1000 years di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance in that his absolute Divine Determination of them, <hi>Rev,</hi> 20.5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry observable in our Appendix to our Schems, 6 times repeated, thrice absolutely, 1000 years, and thrice relatively those, those, those, 1000 years respecting 3 par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of Satans binding, of the Saints Reigning, and of the Happiness of their State all the said 1000 years.</p>
            <p>Which he 2. proves by Scripture Prophesie, of the promised mercies to the faithful Forefathers and to their Spritual seed through Christ in the inteim of the said 1000 years, betwixt both (as in our Proscheme) eternally decreed, and then to be performed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> What Foundation are there of that great Comprehensive mercies of Christ Kingdom on the Earth, which the Scripture teaches shall be at his appearance, when he shall Judge Quick and Dead. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> First, God declares at mans fall, that Christ the promised Seed should breake the Serpents head, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and then at his 2. coming making his Foes his Footstool, should then obtain the headship himself, and become (as was Decreed) Gods King upon his holy Hill of <hi>Sion.</hi> 2. <hi>Balaam</hi> in his Prophesie foretold that his Scepter should come from <hi>Israel, Numb.</hi> 24. 3ly. <hi>Daniel</hi> set forth the time when, <hi>viz.</hi> at the end of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, when the first Judgment is set to destroy the Beast, and to give his Body to the burning Flame. <hi>Dan</hi> 7.11.13, 14. 4ly. his Kingdom was Typified in <hi>Davids,</hi> of whom he came according to the Flesh: But 5. it is many ways explained by Christ himself, in the Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> but chiefly <hi>Ch.</hi> 20. Of this Kingdom we have set down 12. Foundations, from the beginning of <hi>Genesis,</hi> to the end of the Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> in our Tract of the Doctrine of Christs Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> What Foundation was there for the great, holy, and beloved New <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> that comes down from God, out of Heaven with Christ, to be then the Bride the Lambs Wife, being the Spirits of just men-made perfect, to receive their Bodies in their Paradisian restored Sate, to be on Earth the 1000 years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> It was so far revealed to <hi>Abraham, Jsaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> with the promise of <hi>Canaan</hi> in the time of that renewed State, that they are said to see the promise afar off, <hi>viz.</hi> at the Resurrection of the just, when all promised mercies to the Fathers in Christ were to be accomplished, and particularly <hi>Abraham, Heb.</hi> 11. is said to look for a City that hath Foundations whose Maker and Builder is God, such as that City will then be, and <hi>ver.</hi> 16 God (saith the Apostle) hath prepared for them a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205945:2"/>City, and it is gloriously described by Christ, then to come down from God out of Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. of which that given to their natural race was but a Type, and but eonditionally, and was forfeited by their Sin, and destroyed at their Babyle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Captivity 2300 years before the setting up of this glorious New <hi>Jerusalem</hi> in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> What other blessedness belongs to that time and state?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> To this blessedness will be added the Annexing thereunto the Nations of them that are then saved, walking in the light of that great holy and beloved New <hi>Jerusalem</hi> all the said 1000 years, as our Saviour teacheth out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie of <hi>Esay. Rev.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> What further addition will be to that blessedness?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Then also will be the times of the Restiturion of all things which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20. were spoken of by the mouth of all the holy Prophets since the world began, when God will make all things New, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5, as we have shewed in a Treatse upon that Text, when the Curse, Bondage, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and corruption brought in by Sin and Satan, before shall be abolished with that which will compleat the happiness of that time and state: That the Tabernacle of God in Christs humanity will then also be with men, and he will dwell with them that said 1000 years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> Will there be two personal comings of Christ to Judgment at the two said bodily Resurrections, a 1000 years distant one from another?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Yes,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> How are they distinguished in Scripture?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> The former is called his 2. coming, or as <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. when God will bring again his first begotten Son into the world, which the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> (who was rapt up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the 3. Heavens) usufally calls his appearance, because he will then only appear in the Clouds or with Clouds to mortal Eyes, (ordinarily) that they in the natural life with the Converted <hi>Jews, Rev.</hi> 1.7. may so behold him, whose brightness of glory could not otherwise de indured by their Natural Eyes; and this is adjoyned with many of those Excellencies that shall then take place, as his Judging Quick and Dead, (as was shewed) at his appearance, and his Kingdom which will then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. again at that glorious appearance of him the great God and our Saviour Jesus Christ, will be the blessed hope that he teacheth the Saints to wait for, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.13. now that blessed hope is the hope of <hi>Jsrael,</hi> when all promised mercies to the Fathers will take place at the first Resurrection which he so clearely explaines, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.6, 7, 8 unto which hope (saith he) our 12 Tribes instantly serving God day and night hope to come, and then expostulates with them saying: Why should it be thought a thing incredible that God should raise the dead? He also teacheth 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.8. that by this appearance Antichrist shall be destroyed, as was more fully set forth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. that then the Judgment was set at the said first Act thereof; and the Books were opened because of the great words the Horn spake, and in the Ishue the Body of the Beast was given to the burning Flame, he is also said to come at his appearance with all his Saints. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 3. and last 4.14. when all the Angels shall also worship him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. as was foretold, <hi>Ps.</hi> 97. also at his appearance the Saints with the Apostles shall possess their rest. 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.7. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that rest that remains for the people of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. which will be the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batisme of the worlds being: But his last descending with a Shout, and the voice of an Arch-Angel and the Trump of God which St. <hi>Saul</hi> calls the last Trump when he sheweth those Misteries of the momentany rapture and general change of all the Saints together shall be. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51, 52. at the end, that is as Christ Theacheth, 1000 years after his Second coming: For before that time all the Saints could not be rapt at once together, since multitudes of them had not being before nor thence forward be ever with the Lord, since his last coming was not until then, [and these 2 personal comings we have further set forth in 11 or 12 distinctions of them according to the holy Scripture, in Page 1. of the Resurrection upon <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 20.5.]</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:205945:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> What proof is there of the first Act of Judgment at Christs appearance, or the first Resurrection and what will then be done?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> It is excellently set forth in the Song of Praise by the 24 Elders, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 18.19. that God had thus judged not only to destroy them that destoryed the Earth that is chiefly the Turk and Pope with Temperal destruction (the same for time with <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. at the end of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchie,) but also to reward his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Prophets and his Saints, but all that fear his Name both small and great, for (so saith Christ,) when he cometh then his reward is with him, <hi>viz.</hi> for all his Saints both raised and then living. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> What will be done at the last Act of Judgment, after the last <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog</hi> are destroyed by fire from Heaven. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.7.8. after the 1000 years are ended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> At the last Triump when the general momaintany Rapture and change of all Saints shall be at once, to meet the Lord in the Air, thenceforth ever to be with him, the Wicked shall be raised to the last Judgment, to receive the Sentence of Condemnation, to be ever seperated from him unto everlasting Torments in Hell with the Devil and his Angels, (as Christ himself hath taught us.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> What other decypherings doth the holy Scripture give to the time and and State of the said 1000 years?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Sometime it is called the world to come, even an habitable world (as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> denotes,) as the world before the Flood was called the old world, and this present Evil world subject to Satan, stiled (by Usurpation) the God of this world <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> So that world to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. which will begin when God brings his Son again, or the Second time into the world (for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are to be taken adversatively not copulatively as translated, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is of future signification, when he shall again bring his Son, <hi>&amp;.</hi>) as foretold, <hi>Psal.</hi> 97. Again our Saviour Christ, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35. sets it forth by that world of the Resurrection of the just, which are the Children of God, and called there by himself the Children of the Resurrection, who (he saith) shall be counted worthy of that world as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled for it, as the word denotes. Also it is the time of the Restitution of all things, and of the New Heavens and New Earth, spoken of by all the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets since the world began. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20. And therefore is no new or strange Doctrine as many are apt to conceive of it, but is now seriously to be considered and embraced, when it is near approaching at the end of the 2300 years of the <hi>Jews</hi> Bondage at Christs said appearance; which is, and ought to be accounted great matter of Consolation to Christs afflicted and persecuted Church and People in these last Days of Satans, and Antichrists Usurpation and Tyranny; when Christ is shortly coming to put an end to them, even when the <hi>Matutina resurrectio</hi> and <hi>Judicium,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when the just shall have <hi>Domination</hi> in the morning as saith the Psalmist, <hi>Ps.</hi> 49.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quefi.</hi> What Evidence doth the holy Scripture afford of the <hi>Jews</hi> deliverance, and the first bodily Resurrection to be at Christs appearance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> First of the <hi>Jews</hi> deliverance, <hi>Daniel</hi> saith expresly <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.2. at the standing up of <hi>Michael</hi> their Prince <hi>Daniels</hi> People shall be delivered, when the <hi>Turk</hi> that sought their ruin comes to his end, and none could help him in the <hi>Chap.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Secondly, from the frame and order of Scriptures respecting that People, for both <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Joshua</hi> at their Death severely threatened them, if they revolted from from their Covenant, (which they soon did) foretelling their long and sore and most miserable Bondage, as also do those prophetical threatnings, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>Levi.</hi> 26. and that prophetical Song of <hi>Moses, Deut.</hi> 32. accordingly <hi>Jsrael</hi> was led Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive into <hi>Assyria,</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> into <hi>Caldea,</hi> when all the 12. Tribes were in Bondage, but even then God revealed to <hi>Dan.</hi> first by <hi>Nehuchad-nezzars</hi> Image, and by the Vision of the 4 Beasts to himself, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> should have the Dominion all the times of these 4 Monarchies until Christs appearance, or <hi>Michaels</hi> said standing up, as <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.2. And to <hi>Ezek.</hi> also was then shewed upon the tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Crown and Diadem from the last King of <hi>Judah Zedekah;</hi> God would bring 3 great Overturnings by <hi>Babylon, Greece,</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> until he came whose right it is. (as <hi>Dan</hi> 7.13, 14.) and God said then he would give it him, <hi>viz.</hi> Christ. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.26, 27.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:205945:3"/>
            <p>This large time is also exactly computed in a misterious manner by <hi>Palmoni,</hi> or Christ the secret Number to be 2300 years, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.14. (See the reasons on that <hi>ver</hi> in our Summarie of <hi>Dan.</hi>) the period of which great mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ical Number appears to be the period of all other considerable Numbers in <hi>Dan.</hi> and Revelation to be at Christs appearance also, when with the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Isralites</hi> great Restauration concurs the first Resurrection of the just, the Davidical Kingdom of Christ, the Destruction of the man of Sin, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2. and of the <hi>Turk</hi> also, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38. and 39 <hi>ver.</hi> 8.9 in that great Testimony of God himself, [Behold it is come and it is done saith the Lord God; this is the day wherof I have spoken.] Which Divine mark there, (it is done) is set, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.7. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.6. to shew the Popes destruction at the 6t Vials ending, and the concidence of the times of Restitution coming on: So also the mistical, 1666 from Christs Ascension about 34 years from his Birth, pointing out the end of the Beast, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. all agreeing in the same period, as also <hi>Daniels</hi> happy times with his own standing up in his lot then with <hi>Job, David</hi> and all Saints at 1235 years from <hi>Julian</hi> the Apostates 365, (probably) when God last wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully took away Sacrifice. See our Appendix after our Scheme, Pag. 8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> Why are but 3 overturnings mentioned by <hi>Ezek.</hi> in all the 4 said Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> It is probable because none was to be in the <hi>Persian,</hi> but contrarily God would then reduce the 2 Tribes to fulfil his promised mercies to <hi>Judah</hi> by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compleshed his good purpose in sending the <hi>Messiah</hi> at the end of <hi>Daniels</hi> Weeks, by tht Blessed effects of whose Death, Resurrection, and Ascension, should an end be put to the Guilt of Believers transgressions, when the Power and Punishment thereof by everlasting Righteousness is brought to them, are taken away, <hi>&amp;c. Dan.</hi> 9. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the time long before foretold by <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 40. of <hi>Shiloes</hi> or Christs first com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, from which in the times of Revelation Prophesie, many things were to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished for about 1600 years, until his Second coming; ending the last Gentil Monarchy, and the bringing in of Christs most Divine and glorious Kingdom and Monarchy, who then will be manifest to be the King of Kings, and Prince of the Kings of the Farth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. whose Name is wonderful Counseller, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then sitting upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> as <hi>Es.</hi> 9.6.7.</p>
            <p>Hence St. <hi>Paul</hi> so remarkably enjoyneth all Christians, to wait for the Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed hope and glorious appearance of the great God, and our Saviour Jesus Christ. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13. (which we mentioned before.) Now that blessed hope is the hope of <hi>Israel,</hi> or Redemption of <hi>Israel</hi> at Christs Second coming, and the first said Resurrection, when the promised mercies to the Fathers shall especially take place; which the Apostle evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently explains, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.6, 7, 8. of the Resurrection of the Dead then to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished; read and observe his Words well.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="admonition">
            <head>An admonition to all. 1. <hi>For the use of all faithful Christians, whose Duty in general is to own, believe, improve, and promote in their Stations all the Divine Doctrins of the Gospel of Christ.</hi> 2. <hi>For others to seek earnestly for true Repentance towards God, and true Faith in Jesus Christ, that they may receive the Inheritance among them that are Sanctified.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ANd 1. Let it be well observed by all such, that the very express and strong Evidence set down by Christ himself. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. <hi>viz.</hi> of the first blessed bodily Resnarecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Saints, to be 1000 years before the rest of the dead is beyond all denial, to all sober rational men upon many accounts (as may by the following Treatise upon that Text be sufficiently manifest,) and therefore the contrary, long prevailling but groundless mistake and Errour, <hi>viz.</hi> that there will be but one only general Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection at once both of good and bad, (expresly contrary to our Saviours Divine Doctrine thereof) and otherwise also, not only without but contrary to Scripture warrant, must needs be both a groundless and dangerous errour, tending to exclude all other Divine Doctrines of Christ, in his own Revelation that respect the world to come. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. or the glorious and blessed State of his own Mediatory or Davidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205945:3"/>Kingdom. But the owning of that distinct Doctrine of Christ, of the 2 bodily Resurrections at 1000 years distance, is so express from Christs own words, that with them the Interin betwixt both of the 1000 years is a great and sure Foundation of many other Divine Truths foretold by his Spirit of Prophesie, manifesting the said first bodily Resurrection to be the necessary inlet for the raised Saints, whereby they become capable of the manifold great happiness; which without their spiritual Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies they could not then enjoy, nor otherwise so eminently serve him as is said <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.3. that his servants shall serve him, where the Throne of God and of the Lamb shall then be in those many particulars so revealed and determined, for the substance of them by Christ himself, upon the Foundations of the Prophets speaking, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. of such things to come on from the 7th Trumpet: When the mistery of God should be finished, [as he spake by his Servants the Prophets] which were part of his own Purchase at his first coming, and in his Divine Book revealed and undertaken to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer upon his Saints at his Second coming. And what though so clear Discoveries of these Divine Misteries have not been so Evidently made in most of Antichrists Date now near to an end, as hath been in these latter Days, or in those next to the Apostles times as learned Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> observed. That Antichristianisme should then obstrct them to the end, that great Enemie might for his time appear and pass to his period, which time of such Darkness and Ignorance God seemed then to wink at, but since in our times he hath given such great Discoveries of them, it is therefore a duty incumbent upon all good Christians now to receive, improve, and promote them in their places, as was very observable in that very Learned and Reverend Dr. <hi>Twisse</hi> in his latter days, though he was Prolocutor before, of that Learned Assembly mostly of contrary Opinion. Yet was credibly reported, that above what light he had received in them, by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course with Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> (as their Printed Letters manifest) it afterwards so wrought upon his mind and affections, that in them he was much enlivened and raised towards his end in the embracing and due estimation of them.</p>
            <p>And also that worthily, much Reverend and Renownedly, learned and Religious Bishop <hi>Usher,</hi> upon that little intercourse he had, likewise with Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged much of that Nature also, and doubtless by degrees would have done more if further advantage thereof had been afforded to him: And for my unworthy self who formerly opposed Christs said Personal Reign; yet since by special mercie, having obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many gracious Discoveries have since specially strongly confirmd that as after our Scheme may be seen, and many other things of that Natute, published in my Book for the benefit of others, into whose hands they may come. So that it must needs be griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto me, besides other weighty considerations respecting God or Men or their own selves, to hear not only ordinary Persons, but even many Ministers for want of such Divine Discoveries received and prized by them, (as the said first Resurrection taught by Christ is) to hear them preach in publick though most erroneously, that it is nothing else but Spiritual Regeneration. And also that Christs said Kingdom of the 1000 years shortly to come on Earth, is no other then his providential Kingdom which he ever had as God in the World. To deny his Reign then to be personal though sufficiently confirmed, (as we now said) whereby he will be much more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then the Sun in the glorious state of the world to come. And to call the New <hi>Jerusalem</hi> coming down from God at Christs Second coming: The Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven which is then said evedently <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9. to be the Bride the Lambs Wife: When the Tabernacle of God (in Christs Person) will be with Men, and he dweil with them and be their God, and they his People in the great Solemnity of the Marriage of the Lamb probably all the said 1000 years: Yea and some to reject all those Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Doctrins of Christ in the said 1000 years, wherein the Nations also of them that are saved shall walk in the light of the great, holy, and beloved New <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and that of all People under the whole Heaven, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. when in that glorious and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciou prolonging of Christs days then upon Earth he shall so abundantly see his Seed, when the will of the Lord shall most prosper in his hands as foretold, <hi>Es.</hi> 63. when the greatest Harvest of the Saints is to come in, and all Nations see the Salvation of the God of <hi>Israel:</hi> How great a sin then against God and Christ the Saints raised
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205945:4"/>then, and the Nations then to be saved likewise must the denying of these excellent Divine truths needs be? Yea, and some to reject the thousand years themselves though the number of the thousand years is laid down by our Saviour, as the most exact, strong, and unparallelled Determination of a time to come, that is to be found in the whole World: and indeed fit only for the All-knowing and Almighty and blessed God, so to set down aforehand, who can both fully make it good; and who many thousand years before hath revealed, that he will accomplish that State, with such things as he hath revealed shall be fulfilled in them. Yet my own Ears have heard one in publick say, frivolously and and unworthily of them, That he knew not whether there were 1000 2000, or 10000, with other Scriptures by him perverted, respecting the same; whereunto may be annexed, the Antiscriptural error of such as place the times of restitution of all things after the worlds destruction, of which God saith, <hi>Behold I make all things new, viz.</hi> Visibly at Christs second coming, (as we have have shewed upon <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5.) as the Apostle teacheth, he hath done Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually at his first coming, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. so laying the foundation for the other; with many other gross errors of that kind, especially of such as reckon these Divine and Havenly Doctrines: taught by Christ himself (neer to Blasphemy) to be no better than Carnal Opinions (as I have heard delivered in publick also) But I am not willing to rake any further into this Dunghil, only I mention thus much here for these good purposes. First, to caution others for the time to come, against these or the like mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stakes and errors: And secondly, to admonish all, especiall Ministers of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, to search duly into, and to own, improve, and promote, such precious truths of that part of the Gospel tespecting Christs second coming, containing such happy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of all Saints in them; and not to withstand such great things founded on the Prophets, as the Son of God, whose Testimony of them is said also to be the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Prophesie. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19 10, and left for the special Consolation of his Church in these latter and darker days of Antichrist, when as the Prophet speaks (probably of the times of some of the Vials) it seems to be not Day nor Night, but withal for their comfort they should know in the Evening time it shall be light, <hi>Zac.</hi> 14.7. And thirdiy, that Christians might lay to heart and consider, what a great provocation it must needs now be unto Almighty God, that such Divine truths he in so great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and goodness hath in these respects, so set before such as call themselves his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yea, and his portion too, yet should be no better entertained by them; and that the exceeding glorious excellency of Christ himself, the blessed Mediator, shortly to be manifest to be the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3. Should not only be neglected, but so resisted in the World; which I really believe is a special cause and reason (together with other heart and life Provocations amongst these Christians in these dark days, too obvious to be discerned) why God is still pleased to suffer such pressures to lye so long and heavily upon so many (partly in Doctrin) reformed Christian Protestant Churches, in that such light is withholden from most Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans amongst them that discovers their deliverance approraching, and the comfort thereof unto them, and so excellently displays the glory of their great Redeemer, whose glorious appearance will cause them to lift up their heads with joy, yea, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when by the signs thereof they shall but discern them to be near; which the receiving such Doctrines ar these which Christ hath discovered for their use, in that sacred and most Diivine Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> may much hasten for the exceeding great consolation of all soithful Souls. </p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Amen.</hi>
               <signed>W.S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <head>Some seasonable Revelation discoveries respecting these our times, especially of the seven last Plagues or Vials, with the contemporatie, the <hi>2</hi> Witnesses, and with the <hi>10th</hi> part of the Cities falling, <hi>Rev. 11. &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat we may the better discern the pouring out of the fifth Vial and part of the sixt now passing with other occurrants respecting the times lately past or present, or shortly to come, we shall here set down some hints of the four preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205945:4"/>Vials. The first whereof is said to be poured out upon the Earth of the Beast, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.2. appeared to be when he was manifested unto the Church, to be the Great Antichrist, that before stood firm (in appearance) upon a supposed and pretended <hi>jus Divinum,</hi> and was counted Christs Vicar General, and Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Successor in the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> though most fasly (as Mr. <hi>Ed. Deering</hi> hath made evident) which first Vial was poured out by our <hi>Wickliff</hi> and others which so shaked his Earth and Foundation that he stood upon, that thereupon he had a noysome and grievous fore fell upon his followers: which causeed them to be ever since, such Persecutors of all such as Hercticks, as they call them, because their Earth or Foundation is so removed by them, and having a noysomfore upon them.</p>
            <p>The second Vial seemed to be poured upon the Seas of the Beast, when <hi>Luther</hi> so divulged his Divine Doctrines of the Gospel of Christ, and wrote so vigorously a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst many Popish errours, that the truth, by his means was spread largely in <hi>Germany,</hi> and many other Countries, and so took place, that Popish delusions and errors, which prevailed before amongst them, were thereupon cast off, and the Popes power great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diminished in those places, and all his Spiritual delusions amongst them became like the blood of a dead man, having no Life, or Spirits left in them; and this was also wonderful in these two first pourers forth of the said Vials, after their great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency against the man of Sin, and his great endeavours to destroy them successively; yet such was Gods care over them, after all assaults, that they both died peaceably in their Beds, notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>The third Vial, saith Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> was poured out upon the Rivers and Fountains of the Beast, whereby his poysonous Waters were carried and conveyed to the several parts of the World; to wit, by those his Emissaries, the Priests, Friers and Jesuits, the promoters of his wicked Doctrines, by the restraint of penal Laws, to take away their lives, as was made against them in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Raign, and elsewhere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so restrained in other places, the Justice, of which proceeding to give them blood to drink as they were worthy is so greatly celebrated with praise to God, <hi>v.</hi> 5.6.7.</p>
            <p>The fourth Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> conceives also to be poured upon the Sun in the Popes Orb, <hi>viz.</hi> On the <hi>German</hi> Empire, or house of <hi>Austria,</hi> by that illustrious <hi>Gustauus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphus</hi> King of <hi>Sweden</hi> and others over-ruuning suddenly about 200 Miles in their warrs (as was conceived) and though it still remains; yet both then and since have been much weakened by the <hi>Turk</hi> about new <hi>Hausel,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Wars since, for it is to be observed, that no Vial utterly destroys but the last, they only bring the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into a Consumption; yet upon such scorching they have accordingly blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Gods name, and will not acknowledge his hand, and therefore do not repent to give him glory. But the fourth Vial is also conceived to be the casting off the Popes Universality, which before was as his shining Sun that hath darkned his Orb greatly: which appears very probable to be meant thereby.</p>
            <p>The fifth Vial Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> most probably conceived also to be poured out upon the Popes Mystical Throne, to wit, upon Prelacy, or Hierarchical Episcopacy held by the Papists and their party to be <hi>(jure Divino)</hi> whence also Archbishops, Pattiarchs, and Popes act also <hi>(jure Divino)</hi> as sitting upon a Throne: As for what Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of <hi>Rome</hi> as a tenth part of what it was formerly seems too litteral compared with the other Vials; neither was the time of <hi>Rooms</hi> ruin to be expected so soon as the fifth Vial, and also the fall of the tenth part of the great City is quite another thing in others account shortly to be amongst us, towards the end of the great Earth-quake (probably) at the finishing of the Ascention of the last finishing Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, whose Killing Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> himself conceived would be about the fifth Vial, in the <hi>Plateia civitatis</hi> where the fall of that tenth Part or Province of the said great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is probably by divers expected to be, and as a Key for the place, where the last finishing sackcloth Witness should be slain, it is described to be [<hi>where our Lord was crucified, Rev.</hi> 11.8.] as being the Stage of Gods emminent actings, in pouring out the fifth Vial, upon that mystical Throne of the Beasts, <hi>viz. jus Divinum prelaticum</hi> pretended to for setting up their humane institutions, and imposing them more than Gods Divine appointments (as that Hierarchie not long before Christs death did in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205945:5"/>
               <hi>Juden,</hi> whereby civil censures were to be executed, making way for the civil death of the said Witnesses, of which much might be said answerably, † though good men formerly in that capacity, were then content with their <hi>jure humane</hi> from men and end eavoured to serve Christ, in writing against Popish errours, and in promoting Godliness, or were sufferers for the truth, as Bishop <hi>Jewel,</hi> Bishop <hi>Hooper,</hi> Bishop <hi>Latimer,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop <hi>Morton,</hi> Bishop <hi>Babington,</hi> Bishop <hi>Davenant,</hi> &amp;c. But in succeeding times, when after about 17 years voiding of Parliaments, Bishop <hi>Laud,</hi> and Bishop <hi>Wren,</hi> with other of their Party in carrying on such Popish Designs in two Kingdoms at once, (as would then apparently have ruined themselves) did bring in Alters and many al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations in Doctrines and Practises to promote Popery, and therewith a new Book of Cannons with an Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To establish their pretended <hi>jus Divinum</hi> upon their Brethrens Consciences: then God by a Parliament fitted for that work in Forty two, seemed to pour out his Fifth Vial in that <hi>Plateia civitatis</hi> (many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ays like to <hi>Judea</hi>) upon the said Prelacy as tke mistical Throne of the Beast that made the whole Antichristian Kingdom full of Darkness, and caused them to gnaw their Tongues for pain and Blasphem the God of Heaven, overlooking both his Word and Hand therein; imputing all to Mens Sins and Rebellion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented not of their deeds, but only being thereby revengfully carried on to kill the said Witnesses fully, after about 18 years space of their own Suffering; to contrive and prepare for their last great Slaughter, when <hi>Viis</hi> and <hi>Modis</hi> they could after obtain in advantage to accomplish the same. Which in 18 years more seems to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished from 60, (as particularly might be recounted) and therein to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish what that Prophesie <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. from <hi>ver.</hi> 6. foretold, concerning the said finishing Witnesses in the <hi>Plateia civitatis</hi> (as in an other Paper we have manifested to the beginning of the falling of the Tenth part of the great City in that said <hi>Plateia</hi> or Tenth Province also, which seemed to begin an 78. upon the wonderful doscovery, defeat, and many strange disappointments of that desperatly wicked late Plot, by the watchful and most gracious providence of the great Watchman of <hi>Israel,</hi> which Design though still endeavoured to be carried on by many wicked Polices, Lyes, Slanders, and most Hellish Sham-Plots, which is the manifest depth of Devillisme, and height of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanical Wickedness, so hainously to pervert that Sacred Ordinance of appealing to God, (as if he had forsaken the Earth) as thereby to act in such cruel. abominable, and detestable Designs to take away the Lives of Innocent Men; and even to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Gospel of Christ: All which their pacthings and daubings with such un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered Morter notwithstanding, God will doubtless cause the Walls of their City the sooner to moulder away, and at onee ere long like those of <hi>Jerice</hi> to fall down flat, when it shall be truly said, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that that Tenth part of the City, <hi>viz.</hi> the said <hi>Plateia</hi> spoken of before is actually fallen, to wit, all Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Interest hope and expectation therein is vanquished; even by those means whereby the Enemies endeavoured to establish them, and thereupon is to follow the slaying of those 7000 Names of Men; when Gods hand will appear terrible to the great affrightment of that remnant that will then give glory to the God of Heaven, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. at the end of the Second Woe, when that sudden and strong work of the Lord in judging the great Whore, in undertaking to put it into the hearts and hands of the Kings of the Parth to burn her with Fire, probably under the Sixth Vial, wherein may further be effected the drying up of the Popes mistical Buphrates of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire, or the litteral Euphrates for the passage of the Kings of the <hi>East</hi> to seek their Land, or both, (which I rather expect) while the three unclean Spirits like Frogs are croaking in the Courts of Kings, to gather them to the Battle of the great day of God Almighty, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. after described <hi>c.</hi> 19. when will also be executed the Seventh Vial upon the Air of the Beast; when the Prince of the Power of the Air will probably also be bound, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. for 1000 years, until the finishing, whereof he shall not deceive the Nations any more. All which may shortly be compleated before they are expected by most Men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:205945:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>